Guide to the Harold Nicolson Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Harold Nicolson papers
1886-1968
GEN MSS 614
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
19.51
(30 boxes) + 1 record album storage
Nicolson, Harold, 1886-1968
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Bernard Quaritch, Ltd., on the Chauncey Brewster Tinker Prize Fund and the James Marshall and Marie-Louise Osborn Collection Fund, 2012.
Biographical / Historical
Harold George Nicolson (1886-1968) was an English diplomat, biographer, and novelist. He was married to Vita Sackville-West, the English author, poet, and gardener.
Related Materials
Vita Sackville-West Papers (GEN MSS 925). Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Boxes 30-31 (audiovisual materials): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Arrangement
Organized into five series: I. Writings, 1908-1960s. II. Correspondence, 1904-1960s. III. Personal and business papers, 1900s-1960s. IV. Scrapbooks and clippings, 1921-1960s. V. Audiovisual materials, circa 1930s, undated.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of writings, correspondence, personal and business papers, scrapbooks, clippings, and audiovisual materials documenting Harold Nicolson's life and career as a diplomat and author. The papers include drafts and correspondence relating to his biography, King George the Fifth: His Life and Reign (London: Constable, 1952). Correspondence documents his work as both a diplomat and an author, including letters from members of the royal family, members of English literary society, the Foreign Office, civil servant Sir Alan Lascelles (who served as Assistant Private Secretary to George V, among other roles), and his wife Vita Sackville-West. Scrapbooks consist mostly of clippings related to Nicolson.
Authors, British -- 20th Century -- Archives; Diplomats -- Great Britain; Audiovisual materials; Scrapbooks; Diplomats -- Great Britain -- 20th Century; George, King of Great Britain, V, 1865-1936; Lascelles, Alan, Sir, 1887-1981; Nicolson, Harold, 1886-1968; Sackville-West, V. (Victoria), 1892-1962; Great Britain. Foreign Office
- Writings, 1908-1960s; Series I; 6.21; (7 boxes)
  - King George the Fifth manuscripts; speeches, lectures, and radio broadcasts on France, Ireland, elections and, other subjects, 1908-1958 (Box 1)
  - King George the Fifth manuscript; articles, radio broadcasts, and essays relating to nutrition, political life, and other subjects, 1930s-1960s (Box 2)
  - King George the Fifth proofs; notebooks on Curzon and Serbia, 1920s-1950s (Box 3)
  - Contributions to the Spectator; Winston Churchill; World War II; Alexander the Great and other essays, and lectures A-D, 1939-1960s (Box 4)
  - Essays, lectures and, other writings E-Z, 1930s-1960s (Box 5)
  - Notebooks, 1940s-1950s, undated (Box 6)
  - Notebooks, undated (Box 7)
- Correspondence, 1904-1960s; Series II; 8.25; (10 boxes)
  - Alphabetical correspondence
    Arrangement
    Arranged alphabetically by name and subject.
    - Age of Reason - Committees, 1904-1965 (Box 8)
    - Carnock - Greece, 1934-1965 (Box 9)
    - Hamilton - Miscellaneous, 1929-1965 (Box 10)
    - Miscellaneous - Paris Peace Conference, 1916-1965 (Box 11)
    - Paris Peace Conference - Sweet Waters, 1916-1965 (Box 12)
    - Tennyson - Z, 1921-1965 (Box 13)
  - Literary Society correspondence
    - A - Z, 1940s-1960s (Box 14)
    - Additional Literary Society correspondence, 1950-1955 (Box 15)
  - Other correspondence
    - Foreign Office, Retirement Board, circa 1940s-1950s (Box 16)
    - Harold Nicolson letter to Vita Sackville-West and Vita Sackville-West letter to Harold Nicolson, 1948 (Box 17)
    - Lascelles, Alan, Sir, circa 1950s; 1 folder (Box 17)
    - Royal family and related people, circa 1950s; 6 folders (Box 17)
- Personal and business papers, 1900s-1960s; Series III; 1.42; (2 boxes)
  - Financial documents, daybooks, 70th birthday greetings and material relating to Harold Nicolson's death., circa 1950s-1960s (Box 18)
  - Diaries, sketchbooks, awards, degrees, 1900s-1960s (Box 19)
  - Typscript of a scene written by Vita Sackville-West, 1933; 1 folder (Box 19)
- Scrapbooks and clippings, 1921-1960s; Series IV; 3.42; (10 boxes)
  - Scrapbook, 1921-1930 (Box 20)
  - Scrapbook, "Byron the Last Journey", 1924 (Box 21)
  - Scrapbook, 1927-1930 (Box 22)
  - Scrapbooks, " King George the Fifth ," "People and Things, New Spirit in Literature and miscellaneous articles", 1930-1952 (Box 23)
  - Scrapbooks, 1930s-1950s (Box 24)
  - "Scrapbook part I", circa 1936 (Box 25)
  - "Scrapbook part 2", circa 1940s (Box 26)
  - Scrapbook, The Spectator, 1943-1947 (Box 27)
  - Press clippings and scrapbooks, 1940s-1960s (Box 28)
  - Scrapbook, Harold Nicolson "diaries volume I", 1960s (Box 29)
- Audiovisual materials, circa 1930s, undated; Series V; 0.21; (1 box) + 1 record album storage
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - "Modern English Poetry Reading The Swabbert, by Dorothy Wellesley and Sailing to Byzantium, by W.B. Yeats," 78 rpm record, circa 1930s (Box 30 (Record album storage))
  - Untitled, undated; 1; 00:10:21; Program begins abruptly. (Box 31, Item barcode 39002099362429)
    Scope and Contents
    There is a young girl singing on this recording. There is also a conversation regarding a play.